Research Material on Amedeo Modigliani
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Research material on Amedeo Modigliani
circa 1920-1962, bulk circa 1950s
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
d'Atri, Alberto G.
2.1 linear feet
Research material on Amedeo Modigliani, circa 1920-1962, measures 2.1 linear feet and was compiled by art critic Alberto G. d'Atri for his unpublished work, "La Vie et l'Oeuvre de Modigliani Amedeo, 12 Juillet 1884 - 24 Janvier 1920 par Alberto G. d'Atri," circa 1950-1956. Found is Modigliani's death certificate, correspondence, writings, notes, printed material, reproductions, extensive photographs of artwork, and a register of Modigliani's works of art.
Provenance
The research material on Amedeo Modigliani was donated to the Archives of American Art by Alberto G. d'Atri's daughter, Lisa Claire Martin, in 1995.
Restrictions on Access
The collection is open for research. Use requires an appointment.
Biographical Note
Alberto G. d'Atri was an art critic based in Paris, France. His subject was the Italian painter Amedeo Modigliani (1884-1920).
Scope and Content Note
Research material on Amedeo Modigliani, circa 1920-1962, measures 2.1 linear feet and was compiled by art critic Alberto G. d'Atri for his unpublished work, "La Vie et l'Oeuvre de Modigliani Amedeo, 12 Juillet 1884 - 24 Janvier 1920 par Alberto G. d'Atri," circa 1950-1956. Found is Modigliani's death certificate, correspondence, writings, notes, printed material, reproductions, extensive photographs of artwork, and a register of Modigliani's works of art.
Correspondence includes letters to and from Alberto d'Atri with European and American museums and galleries, and scholars. A significant portion of the correspondence is in French, and to a lesser extent, Italian. Writings consist of typed manuscripts, drafts, and research notes, primarily in French. Notes include lists of Modigliani's works of art in the collections of museums, galleries, and private owners, and notes for an exhibition catalog of the artist's works.
Printed Material includes a handful of photocopied clippings, two exhibition announcements, and scattered articles and essays on Modigliani. Found among the reproductions are facsimiles of letters from Modigliani, prints, postcards and various printed material of Modigliani's artwork. Much of the research material consists of photographs of works of arts by Modigliani, many of which have provenance-related information written on the back of the photograph. Also found are a handful of reproduced photographs of Modigliani and his artist friends and models, and d'Atri's oversized one-volume register of Modigliani's works of art which contains 329 entries indicating titles, dimensions, dates, descriptions, ownership, provenance, and exhibition history for each work.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as 8 series:
Series 1: Biographical Material, circa 1950s (Box 1; 1 folder)
Series 2: Correspondence, circa 1948-1962 (Box 1; 0.3 linear feet)
Series 3: Writings, circa 1950-1956 (Box 1; 0.4 linear feet)
Series 4: Notes, circa 1950s-1960 (Box 1; 8 folders)
Series 5: Printed Material, circa 1920-1959 (Box 1; 3 folders)
Series 6: Reproductions of Modigliani's Works of Art, circa 1937-1957 (Box 1; 4 folders)
Series 7: Photographs, circa 1950s-1960s (Box 1-3; 0.9 linear feet)
Series 8: Register of Modigliani's Works of Art, 1908-1920 (Box 4; 0.3 linear feet)
Other than the photographs, the materials in each series likely reflect the original arrangement by d'Atri. The bulk of d'Atri's research and writing appears to have been conducted during the 1950s; therefore, many undated materials have been given the circa date 1950s.
Names and Subject Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following terms:
Subjects:
Modigliani, Amedeo,1884-1920
Subjects-Topical:
Art critics -- France
Types of Materials:
Drafts (documents); Photographs; Notes; Manuscripts
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Biographical Material, circa 1950s, Series 1:; (Box 1; 1 folder)
  - Modigliani's Death Certificate, circa 1950s (Box 1)
- Correspondence, circa 1948-1962, Series 2:; (Box 1; 0.3 linear feet)
  Correspondence includes letters to and from Alberto d'Atri with European and American museums and galleries, and scholars. Some folders contain photographs, notes, and other printed material. A significant portion of the correspondence is in French, and to a lesser extent, Italian.
  Folders are arranged chronologically. Business cards and loose envelopes are filed after correspondence.
  - Correspondence Relating to Portrait of Beatrice Hastings, circa 1948-1958 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, circa 1950
  - Correspondence with Galerie Bing, 1950-1951 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1951 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1952 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence (Romanet Blum), circa 1952-1957 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1953-1954 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1955 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1956-1957 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence with Richard Dervan, 1957-1958 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1958-1960 (Box 1)
  - Undated Correspondence, circa 1950s (Box 1)
  - Business Cards, undated (Box 1)
  - Loose Envelopes (Including Postal Receipts), circa 1951-1962 (Box 1)
  - Undated Loose Envelopes, circa 1950s (Box 1)
- Writings, circa 1950-1956, Series 3:; (Box 1; 0.4 linear feet)
  Writings consist of typed manuscripts with edits, drafts, and research notes. The bulk of the material is in French.
  - "Modigliani: Sa Vie et Son Oeuvre", undated (Box 1)
  - "La Vie et l'Oeuvre de Modigliani Amedeo, 12 Juillet 1884 - 24 Janvier 1920 par Alberto G. d'Atri", circa 1950s, (3 folders; includes photographs)
  - Forward to "La Vie et l'Oeuvre de Amedeo Modigliani", circa 1950s (Box 1)
  - Introduction to "La Vie et l'Oeuvre de Amedeo Modigliani", circa 1950s (Box 1)
  - Drafts for "La Vie et l'Oeuvre de Amedeo Modigliani", circa 1950s (Box 1)
  - Drafts for Catalogue des Oeuvres de Amedeo Modigliani, circa 1950s (Box 1)
  - Typescripts on Modigliani, circa 1950-1956 (Box 1)
  - Typescripts on Modigliani by d'Atri, circa 1950s (Box 1)
  - Typescripts of a Talk by d'Atri, circa 1950s (Box 1)
- Notes, circa 1950s-1960, Series 4:; (Box 1; 8 folders)
  Notes include lists of Modigliani's works of art in the collections of museums, galleries, and private owners, and notes for an exhibition catalog of the artist's works. The bulk of the material is in French.
  Folders are arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - Exhibition Lists of Modigliani's Works of Art, circa 1950s, (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Lists of Modigliani's Artwork in the Collections of Museums, Galleries, and Owners, circa 1950s, (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Notes for Catalog, 1954, undated (Box 1)
  - d'Atri's Research Material on Raphael, 1960, undated (Box 1)
  - Various Notes, 1951-1958, undated (Box 1)
  - Various Notes, undated (Box 1)
- Printed Material, circa 1920-1959, Series 5:; (Box 1; 3 folders)
  Printed Material includes a handful of photocopied clippings, two exhibition announcements, and scattered articles and essays on Modigliani. The bulk of the material is in French.
  Folders are arranged alphabetically by type of material.
  - Clippings (Photocopies), circa 1958-1959 (Box 1)
  - Exhibition Announcements, 1952, 1958 (Box 1)
  - Various Printed Material Including Reviews on Modigliani's Work, circa 1920-1952 (Box 1)
- Reproductions of Modigliani's Works of Art, circa 1937-1957, Series 6:; (Box 1; 4 folders)
  Reproductions includes facsimiles of letters from Modigliani (circa 1908-1909), prints, postcards and various printed material of Modigliani's artwork.
  - Reproductions, 1953, 1956, undated (Box 1)
  - Reproductions of Works of Art, circa 1937-1957 (Box 1)
  - Reproductions of Works of Art, circa 1950s, (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Reproductions of Works of Art, Postcards, undated (Box 1)
- Photographs, circa 1950s-1960s, Series 7:; (Box 1-3; 0.9 linear feet)
  Found are numerous black and white photographs of works of art by Modigliani. On the back of many photographs, d'Atri has written in French provenance-related information of the artwork. Some folders also contain letters, notes, and certification documentation. In addition, there are a handful of reproduced photographs of Modigliani, his artist friends and models, and scattered photographs of artwork by various other artists.
  Photographs have been minimally arranged in a loose chronology based on the creation date of the earliest artwork in the folder, as indicated on the back of the photograph. Most folders are further arranged by the artwork's subject matter or type of material.
  - Works of Art by Modigliani (Box 1)
    - (1904-1919), circa 1950s (Box 1)
    - Portraits (circa 1905-1913), circa 1950s (Box 1)
    - Portraits (circa 1906-1917), circa 1950s (Box 1)
    - Primarily Male Portraits (circa 1907-1919), circa 1950s (Box 1)
    - Female Portraits (circa 1908-1919), circa 1950s, (3 folders) (Box 1)
    - Portraits (circa 1908-1919), circa 1950s (Box 1)
    - Portraits (circa 1908-1920), circa 1950s (Box 1)
    - Pencil Drawings (circa 1908-1918), circa 1950s (Box 1)
    - Pencil Drawings (circa 1908-1919), circa 1950s (Box 1)
    - Sculptures (circa 1909-1910), circa 1950s-1960s (Box 2)
    - Pencil Drawings (circa 1910-1918), circa 1950s (Box 2)
    - Caryatids (circa 1910-1916), circa 1950s (Box 2)
    - Male Portraits (circa 1910-1919), circa 1950s (Box 2)
    - Figures in Pencil (circa 1912-1918), circa 1950s (Box 2)
    - Pencil Drawings (circa 1914-1918), circa 1950s (Box 2)
    - Female Portraits (circa 1914-1919), circa 1950s (Box 2)
    - Female Portraits (circa 1915-1916), circa 1950s (Box 2)
    - Female Portraits (circa 1915-1919), circa 1950s (Box 2)
    - Male Portraits (circa 1915-1919), circa 1950s (Box 2)
    - Primarily Pencil Drawings (circa 1915-1919), circa 1950s (Box 2)
    - Primarily Portraits of Beatrice Hastings (circa 1915-1916), circa 1950s (Box 2)
    - Portraits of Paul Guillaume (circa 1915-1916), circa 1950s (Box 2)
    - Portraits (circa 1915-1917), circa 1950s (Box 2)
    - Primarily Portraits (circa 1915-1918), circa 1950s (Box 2)
    - Portraits of Chaim Soutine (circa 1916-1918), circa 1950s (Box 2)
    - Female Nudes in Pencil (circa 1916-1919), circa 1950s (Box 2)
    - Portraits (circa 1916-1919), circa 1950s (Box 2)
    - (Circa 1916-1920), circa 1950s (Box 2)
    - Portraits of Leopold Zborowksi (circa 1916-1920), circa 1950s (Box 3)
    - Female Portraits (circa 1916-1920), circa 1950s (Box 3)
    - Portraits and Certification Documentation (circa 1916-1919), circa 1950s (Box 3)
    - Primarily Female Portraits (circa 1917), circa 1950s, (2 folders) (Box 3)
    - Female Nudes (circa 1917), circa 1950s (Box 3)
    - Portraits (circa 1917-1919), circa 1950s (Box 3)
    - Portraits (circa 1917-1919), circa 1950s, (Includes letters, notes, and clippings) (Box 3)
    - Portraits of Signora Zechowska (circa 1917-1919), circa 1950s (Box 3)
    - Female Portraits (circa 1917-1920), circa 1950s (Box 3)
    - Primarily Portraits (circa 1918), circa 1950s (Box 3)
    - Sculptures (dates unknown), circa 1950s (Box 3)
    - Undated Artwork, circa 1950s (Box 3)
  - Installation Shots of Modigliani's Works of Arts, circa 1950s (Box 3)
  - Images of Modigliani, Family Members, and Artist Friends (circa 1912-1940s), circa 1950s (Box 3)
  - Various, circa 1950s, (2 folders) (Box 3)
  - Various, Paintings by Other Artists from 1750-1896, undated (Box 3)
- Register of Modigliani's Works of Art, circa 1950s, Series 8:; (Box 4; 1 folder)
  This series is comprised of d'Atri's oversized one-volume register of Modigliani's works of art from 1908-1920. The register includes 329 entries indicating titles, dimensions, dates, descriptions, ownership, provenance, and exhibition history for each work.
  - Register of Modigliani's Works of Art, circa 1950s (Box 4)